Guide to the Russian Posters Collection, 1919-1989 and undated RL.01122
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Russian Posters collection
1919-1989 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01122
4 Linear Feet
The Russian Posters Collection is divided into three series spanning the years 1919 to 1989: 30 posters emphasizing the benefits of communism and the first "Five Year Plan" for workers, the achievements of the USSR under communism, religion as an enemy of the people, and the struggle against and decline of capitalism; 14 placards from the 22nd Congress of the Communist Party of the USSR describing and depicting the strength of the country in industrial development, consumer goods, agricultural production, electrification, and the national welfare; and the collapse of the colonial system of imperialism and the problems facing capitalism; and last, ten posters from the "perestroika" period of the 1980s, most of which were exhibited in Moscow in 1988. In addition, the collection houses nine facsimiles of Russian posters from the 1920s-1930s. The posters have been digitized and are available online.
81 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Russian Posters Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in the early 1960s, 1970s, and 2010.
Posters in the General Political Posters series were a gift of Calvin Bryce Hoover (1897-1974), a member of the Duke faculty, chairman of the Department of Economics (1937-1957) and Dean of the Graduate School (1938-1948).
Collection Overview
The Russian Posters Collection spans a good part of 20th century Russian political history, and is divided into three main groupings: 30 posters emphasizing the benefits of communism and the first "Five Year Plan" for workers, the achievements of the former USSR under communism, religion as an enemy of the people, and the struggle against and decline of capitalism; 14 placards from the 22nd Congress of the Communist Party of the former USSR describing and depicting the strength of the country in industrial development, consumer goods, agricultural production, electrification, and the national welfare, and the collapse of the colonial system of imperialism and the problems facing capitalism; and last, 26 posters from the "perestroika" period of the 1980s, most of which were exhibited in Moscow in 1988. In addition, the collection houses nine facsimiles of Russian posters from the 1920s-1930s. Some posters feature anti-religious slogans. The posters have also been digitized and are available online.
Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1917-1936 -- Posters; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1953-1985 -- Posters; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1925-1953 -- Posters; Soviet Union -- Social conditions -- 20th century -- Posters; Soviet Union -- History -- 1953-1985 -- Posters; Soviet Union -- Religion -- 20th century -- Posters; Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century -- Posters; Posters; Posters, Russian; Facsimiles (reproductions); Kommunisticheskai͡a partii͡a Sovetskogo Soi͡uza -- History; Political posters, Russian; Posters, Russian -- 20th century -- Exhibitions; Communism -- Soviet Union -- Posters; Posters, Soviet Union -- 20th century; Propaganda, Communist -- Soviet Union -- Posters; Communism -- Soviet Union -- Congresses; Soviet Union -- Economic policy -- 1959-1965 -- Posters; Soviet Union -- Economic policy -- 1928-1932 -- Posters; Soviet Union -- History -- 1925-1953 -- Posters; Soviet Union -- History -- 1917-1936 -- Posters
- General Political Posters Series, 1919-1930 and undated, 30 items
  Scope and Contents note
  These political posters from the former Soviet Union cover the period between the end of the "New Economic Policy" and the beginning of the first "Five Year Plan" and cover a range of related issues related to religion, economic and social changes, and political events. Their titles have been translated into English by Raphael Lemkin (1900-1959), most likely during his brief tenure as a visiting instructor in the Duke University Law School (1941-1942). When dates are present they have been added.
  - Snaring the birds, 1930 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Anti-religious farm women prepare to quit old life and move into new life, 1929 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Enemies of the Five Year Plan, circa 1929 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Long live the first of May (Oversize-folder 1)
  - We are preparing to repulse the enemy, 1927 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - All the past will be put into the garbage dump (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Easter: contrast of joyous Easter of long ago with serious workers of Communist Russia (Oversize-folder 1)
  - With the pen and the light of science disclose plots of the sects (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Public nursery (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Stalin: 'Russian Revolution has given national life and development to many groups in Russia' (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Achievement of Russia under communism (published by propaganda division of Russian Communist Party) (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Proletarians of the world unite (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Importance of knowledge for Red Soldiers (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Against capitalistic imperialist wars, Yellow Second International, the League of Nations, leaders and appeasers of the International Cooperative Movement (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Why were 10,000,000 men killed from 1914-1918?, 1929 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - 'Double crosser': the Church (published by the Artists' Society) (Oversize-folder 2)
  - The way to the Russian Revolution and the world revolution (2 copies) (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Struggle against religion is a struggle for communism (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Propaganda for Young Communist Pioneers (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Women workers of the Orient, free yourself, enter the workforce, work at the collective farm, join the ranks of the builders of socialism, 1930 (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Red Army training (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Member of a religious sect is fooling the people (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Struggle against religion is a struggle for socialism, The Athiest at Work [journal] supplement (Oversize-folder 3)
  - The best answer to the designs of imperialism is a strong industrialization and a spirit of cooperation (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Fighting against illegal alcohol (from the Propaganda Division of the Head Department of Political Education) (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Capitalistic and communistic conceptions of the army (Oversize-folder 3)
  - The saviors of the world: founders of world religions (Oversize-folder 3)
  - The coming of Lenin to Petrograd in 1917 (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Ironical poster about Christmas, supplement from The Atheist at Work [journal] (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Go to the collective farms (anti-kulak) (Oversize-folder 3)
  - Leningrad (Oversize-folder 3)
    Travel poster (2011 acquisition).
- Electioneering Placards: Twenty-Second Communist Party Congress Series, 1960-1962, 14 items
  Electioneering placards related to the 22nd Congress of the Communist Party of the former Soviet Union. The titles have been translated into English.
  - Twenty-second Congress of the SPSU - Congress of communism's builders, Moscow, Oct. 17-31, 1961 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - The transformation of the socialist system into a decisive factor of world development (Oversize-folder 4)
  - The collapse of the colonial system of imperialism (Oversize-folder 4)
  - New strain on capitalism's general crisis (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Further strengthening of the economic might of the USSR, 1956-1961, 1962 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Seven year employment plan, 1962 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Further strengthening of the economic might of the USSR, 1956-1961, 1961 (heavy industry statistics) (Oversize-folder 4)
  - The rise of agricultural production, 1956-1960 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - The growth in national welfare in 1956-1960 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - A general perspective of USSR industrial development, 1961-1980 - capital investment (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Electrification - pivot in the building of the communist economy, 1961-1980 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - A general perspective of USSR industrial development, 1961-1980 - production goals (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Master-plan of development of the USSR's agricultural sector, 1961-1980 (Oversize-folder 4)
  - Rise in the national material welfare, 1961-1980 (Oversize-folder 4)
- Facsimile Posters Series, 1920s-1930s, 9 items
  Facismiles of former Soviet Union posters from the 1920s and 1930s. Dates are approximate.
  - 7th anniversary of the October Revolution, 1925-1928 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Join the Red cavalry!, 1920-1939 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Last hour, 1920 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Under the red flag..., 1920-1939 (women marching against a lone capitalist who is falling before them) (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Help! Join the ranks of the MOPR!, 1920-1939 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Revolution of 1905, 1920-1939 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Red Army defense of the proletarian revolution, 1920-1939 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Enemy wants to capture the heart of Moscow, Soviet Russia, 1920-1939 (Oversize-folder 5)
  - Road to Communism, 1920 (Oversize-folder 5)
- Perestroika Era Posters Series, circa 1980-1989, 26 items
  An assemblage of posters, arranged in two subgroupings, from the decade prior to the break-up of the Soviet Union, about 1980 to 1989. All except one of these posters formed an exhibit held in Moscow in 1988; ten reproductions are in their own exhibit folder. One poster from an anti-alcoholism campaign unrelated to the exhibit but from the same period closes the series. The transcribed title is followed by the English translation. Authors and artists's names are also given; in some cases there is more than one name. Some posters are composites of more than one poster; and one poster consists of three sheets. Posters are in original order as received.
  - Exhibit Posters Subseries, 13 items
    Consists of a cover folder that describes the 1988 Moscow poster exhibit and which contains reproductions of ten posters, one of which is a triptych. The cover folder for the posters reads, "Soiuz khudozhnikov SSSR.; Soiuz khudozhnikov RSFSR.; Moskovskaia organizatsiia Soiuza khudozhnikov RSFSR. Plakat-perestroike: komplekt-vystavka (Moskva: "Plakat," 1988)."
    - Cover folder, poster exhibition, 1988 (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Invalidy bol'she ne mogut zhdat'. [The disabled can wait no longer.] Kacher, O. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Pravda. [Truth.] Belozerov, G. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Chto delat'? [What is to be done?] Cherenov, V., A. Reshetov and V. Kozlov (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Narod, zabyvshii svoiu istoriiu… [A people that forgets its own history…] Kovaleva, L. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - 1929. Kollektivizatsiia. [1929: Collectivization.] Vaganov, A. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Kadry reshaiut vse (3 lista). [Party cadres decide all.] Kondurov, A., 3 sheets, total of 6 images (Oversize-folder 6)
    - 1935, 1936, 1937....1940. (Deportation train with ghostly images) Lozenko, A. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Venets--delu konets. [All's well that ends well.] Mosienko, S. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - U menia est' svoe mnenie, no ia s nim nesoglasen. [I have my own opinion, but I do not agree with it.] Leonov, Iu. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Spasite! [Help!] (Dog with sewn leather patch on ear and price tag - protesting selling of dog furs?) Sukharev, S. (Oversize-folder 6)
    - ?000,000... [no translation; shows pyramid of red hands against dark background] (Oversize-folder 6)
  - Prize-winning Exhibit Posters Subseries, 12 items
    Consists of prize winners from the same 1988 exhibit. Two of the posters have two additional images, besides the one represented by the title. There are actually 16 images, as several posters are composites of more than one poster. Arranged in order from first prize to runners-up.
    - Nash schet. 707. [Our account. 707.] Tarasov, I. (1st prize) (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Pravil'no poniat' proshloe -- znachit oblegchit' poiski vernogo puti v budushchee. [Correctly understanding the past eases the search for a true path to the future.] Lekomtsev, A., E. Morozovskii, O. Staikov. II premiia (2nd prize) (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Doloi pokazukhu! [Down with showing-off!] Chervotkin, N. II premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Pamiat'. [Memory.] Sidorova, M., L. Kaushanskii. III premiia (3rd prize) (Oversize-folder 6)
    - S dnem rozhdeniia, Komsomol! [Happy Birthday, Komsomol (Young Communist League)!] Faldin, A., R. Akmanov. III premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Stalinizm. [Stalinism.] Leonov, Iu. III premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Zabota -- eto rabota! [Caring takes work.] Vasil'chenko, A. Pooshchritel'naia premiia (runner-up) (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Popalas'! (A triptypch image of three posters, including these other two: Segal', A., A. Faldin, "Kaby chego…"; and Budanov, Iu., "Tiazhelyi metal") [(1) Caught! (2) So as not to… (3) Heavy metal.] Reznikov, I, S. Vasil'ev. Pooshchritel'naia premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Vznos Komsomola (2 other posters: Kurashov, I, A. Faldin, A. Faldina, "…Nasha sovest' est' nam luchshii sud'ia"; and Tarasov, A., "Imei svoe litso!" [(1) Komosomol dues; (2) Our conscience is our best judge; (3) Be your own person!] Pivnev, N. Pooshchritel'naia premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Kazhdoi sem'e k 2000 godu… [To every family in the year 2000…] Linnik, I., A. Krent'. Pooshchritel'naia premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Mama! [Mama!]Valiakhmetov, I. Pooshchritel'naia premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
    - Novyi den' budu stroit' sam. [I will build the new day myself!] Kovalenko, V. Pooshchritel'naia premiia (Oversize-folder 6)
  - Other Posters, 1 item
    - Ot pervoi sladkoi riumochki… [From the first sweet wine glass...] Teplitskaia, I.(Moskva: Izd-vo "Plakat", 1989) (Oversize-folder 6)
      Perestroika-era poster, unrelated to the 1988 Moscow exhibit, deals with the Soviet government's anti-alcohol campaign.